Today's דף daf. *daf* is כ"ט *Kaf Tet* and we have a
couple of really nice topics to wrap up and to also cover.
We were in the middle of a whole discussion of the debate
of רב Rav, ושמואל *Rav u'Shmuel* about here somebody who trips on
some water or a broken vessel, is that considered to be a
שור shor. *Shor* or בור bor *Bor*? That's the classic question about
something that you owned that's in רשות הרבים reshus harabim *Reshus Harabim*
and a hazard that you still own. רב *Rav* says it's a
type of a generic שור *Shor* and שמואל *Shmuel* says it's a
בור bor. *Bor*.
And therefore for רב *Rav*, you're חייב chayav, *chayav* if it damages
vessels, like if it's water and it stained your garment or it
was a rock and it ripped your garment. And שמואל *Shmuel* says
no, it's a בור bor *Bor* even though you own it and
you own normally things you own are like animals that go out
and gore or whatever, fundamentally it's a hazard, it's a בור bor
*Bor*, and that means that any damage to vessels you'd be פטור
patur. *patur*. And we spent most of the כ"ט עמוד ב' *Kaf
Tet Amud Bet* yesterday trying to bring like ברייתות *Baraisos* to prove
one way or the other according to רב ושמואל *Rav u'Shmuel* whether
it's a שור *Shor* and a בור bor *Bor*. A related debate
that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is not focusing on now but will
come up later is then the guy trips over it and hits
himself on the ground. So how much are you חייב chayav, *chayav*
for the guy that hurts himself on the ground? So רב *Rav*
says you're פטור patur. *patur*. If you tripped over my, if my
ox pushed you to the ground, interestingly, I would think you should
be חייב chayav. *chayav*, your ox pushed me to the ground. But
since ultimately the damage occurred not on the horns of the ox
but on the impact of the ground, רב *Rav* says you're going
to be פטור patur. *patur*. And שמואל *Shmuel* says no, if you
trip on it and hurt yourself on the ground, that's like an
extension of the בור bor, *Bor* and you are going to be
חייב chayav *chayav*. Okay, so those are two debates of רב ושמואל
*Rav u'Shmuel*. We now pick up in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* on
the bottom of כ"ח עמוד ב' *Kaf Chet Amud Bet* and the
גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says like this. אמר amar רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar,
*Amar Rabbi
Elazar*,
it is the line starts with the words סלוכיתא *Sloochisa* and it
is five, eight, ten, fifteen lines from the bottom. Well, not just
before the two dots. Fifteen lines from the bottom, סלוכיתא *Sloochisa*. Okay,
so it says in the middle of that line. אמר רבי אלעזר
Rebi Eleazar *Amar Rabbi Elazar*, לא שנו אלא ella שנתקל באבן ונשף
באבן *Lo shanu ela she-nitkal be-even ve-nishaf be-even*. What is the case
that when you trip over the stone you're חייב chayav? *chayav*? If
you trip over the stone and bang on the stone. Now as
we just said, trip over the stone and bang on the ground,
that's a debate of רב ושמואל *Rav u'Shmuel*. But everybody would agree
you trip over the stone and bang on the stone, you're חייב
chayav *chayav*. Okay?
But let's say a case we haven't discussed. נתקל niskal בקרקע ונשף
באבן *Nitkal ba-karka ve-nishaf be-even*. Okay, there are three cases, right? There's
tripping on the stone and banging on the stone, you're חייב chayav.
*chayav*. Tripping on the stone and banging on the ground, the stone
was the hazard like a normal בור bor, *Bor* is a hazard,
but the thing that did the damage was the ground. And then
there's a third scenario. You tripped over your own two feet and
you banged your head on somebody's stone that they left in the
middle of the road. Okay, so the stone didn't act as a
hazard, it acted as the thing to create the damage, but it
didn't create the damage as like something going out and goring like
an ox. Okay, what would be the story there? So let's assume,
I don't know, let's say I tripped over my own two feet
and I impaled myself on the horns of your ox. Okay, so
presumably you'd be פטור patur. *patur*, right? But I don't know, if
your ox didn't have a right to be in the middle of
a רשות הרבים reshus harabim. *Reshus Harabim*, if your stone didn't have
a right to be there, even if I was the one that
sort of began the act of היזק hezek. *hezek* or the act
of tripping, right, or stumbling, how much are you חייב chayav *chayav*
if you actually impact with my thing that shouldn't be there? So
he says,
so נתקל nitkal? בקרקע ונשף באבן פטור patur. *Nitkal ba-karka ve-nishaf be-even
patur*. You'd be פטור patur. *patur*. All right, the thing the either
whether it's a בור bor *Bor* or a שור *Shor*, it has
to basically be the thing that does the act, you know, begin
the act of damaging,
not that you started the process and then banged into me. Now,
we are going to see by the way, I should say, in
about a minute, we're about to look at an important debate whether
נתקל פושע nitkal poshea. *nitkal poshea* or נתקל nitkal, אונס ones, *nitkal
oness*. It's so fascinating, right? The same way like we had a
discussion, are you supposed to watch where you're going or not when
you step on something in the middle of the street? So when
you trip, is it because you're just being you're careless and you
know or no, you know you tripped, it happens sometimes, you know
you're being you're exerting the normal amount of care and nevertheless you
slip and you trip. Okay? So if you say that tripping is
פשיעה peshi'ah, *peshi'ah*, you certainly understand why you'd be פטור patur, *patur*,
right? I'm negligent, I shouldn't have tripped, it's פשיעת הניזק *peshi'as hanizak*,
contributory negligence. All right, but he's not even discussing that, maybe even
if I'm an אונס ones, *oness*, you're going to be פטור patur.
*patur* because in the end of the day, your thing was totally
passive and I basically impaled myself on your thing. Okay, so he
says, אמר נתקל nitkal בקרקע ונשף באבן פטור patur. *Amar nitkal ba-karka
ve-nishaf be-even patur*. כמאן *Ke-man*? Who is that going like? דלא כרבי
נתן *D'lo k'Rabbi Nasan*. Not like רבי נתן Rebbi Nasan, *Rabbi Nasan*.
Now what רבי נתן Rebbi Nasan. *Rabbi Nasan* says is, רבי נתן
Rebbi Nasan, *Rabbi Nasan* says let's say Michael's ox goes ahead and
pushes me into you know into Hillel's בור bor *Bor*. Okay, so
who do I collect from? So רבי נתן Rebbi Nasan. *Rabbi Nasan*
says. רבי נתן Rebbi Nasan, says that basically, if I can’t, whoever
I can. If I can’t collect from Michael, I can collect from
Hillel. Okay, so there’s a case where Hillel’s בור bor, only functioned
as a passive sort of thing that was impacted upon. It didn’t
cause, push me, it didn’t cause me to trip, and nevertheless, it’s
considered to be a participant in the act of me being damaged.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, so let’s say it wasn’t Michael’s
ox, let’s say it was my own two feet, and I tripped
and I fell into Hillel’s בור. bore. So he says, well, לפי
l'fi רבי נתן, if his ox gores it, Hillel is a participant
in the damage, then when I trip on my own two feet
and I fall into his בור bore. and I fall on his
rock, he’s also a participant in the damage. That’s also considered a
מעשה היזק. maise hezek. Now, of course it’s a little bit different,
right? Because you could say even bracketing the question of whether I
was negligent, when it starts by an act of damage defined by
a goring ox, other things could be seen as sort of being
a part of, participating in that act of damage. When it starts
as me tripping over my own two feet, even if there’s no
negligence, then it’s not an act of me being damaged, that’s just
an act of, you know, something happening to me, and the rock
or the בור bore. which is totally passive, you might say, you
know, is not considered to be a to be doing an act
of היזק. Okay, so you could I think you could easily distinguish
between the goring ox where there’s an act of damage that was
initiated and tripping over my own two feet. But the גמרא Gemara
compares it. And it says this would not be like רבי נתן.
According to רבי נתן, the owner of the בור bore would have
to pay, the owner of the stone would have to pay. איכא
דאמרי Ika d'amri some say, אמר רבי אלעזר, לא תימא דנתקל באבן
ונשוף באבן הוא דמיחייב, lo teima d'niskal b'even v'nishaf b'even hu d'mechayev,
don't say only tripping on the stone and banging on the stone
you're
חייב, chayav אבל נתקל בקרקע ונשוף באבן פטור, aval niskal b'karka v'nishaf
b'even patur, don't think that if you trip on the stone and
bang yourself, I'm sorry trip on the ground and bang yourself on
the stone you're going to be
exempt, אלא אפילו נתקל בקרקע ונשוף באבן חייב, ella afilu niskal b'karka
v'nishaf b'even chayav, even if you trip over the ground and bang
yourself on the stone you're
חייב, chayav כמאן כרבי נתן, k'man k'Rebbi Nasan, like רבי נתן. And
that seems to be the second and concluding position of the גמרא.
Gemara So that’s quite surprising. Number one, it assumes that נתקל nitkal
is אונס, ones, that tripping, I’m not negligent for my own tripping,
because if I am negligent then it’s contributory negligence. And number two,
it assumes that rather than looking at the whole thing as just
an accident, right? And even with רבי נתן, there’s no beginning of
an act of מזיק. mazik. It begins with an accident, right? And
even though it begins with an accident, nevertheless we view the stone
that shouldn’t be there as having done a מעשה מזיק. maise mazik.
So it’s quite interesting when the תורה Torah is מחייב mechayev you
for בור, bore. assuming we’re going to call the stone a בור,
bor we have two scenarios. It’s a hazard without doing the act
of damage, you trip on the stone and you damage yourself on
the ground, or it does the act of damage without functioning as
a hazard, right? Those are two halves of what a בור bor,
normally is. Okay, and according to רב, you could ask the same
question about שור. Yes.
I don't understand also this בור ברשות הרבים, bor birshus harabim, does
it make a difference if I put it there intentionally or not?
Does it?
Well, intentionally you mean negligently or not?
Negligently or intentionally, I'm walking and something falls out of my backpack.
Well no, it does make a difference if you were you don't
have to be intentional but you have to be you might have
to be negligent, we're going to get to that.
So let's say I'm walking and something falls out of my backpack,
I had no time to even.
Right, then you're פטור. patur. And that's about we're about to get
to that case.
Wait, I have one more question. And lastly like פושרה דמיא, pshura
d'maya, what I find interesting is how they differentiated whether you're מפקיר
mafkir the water or not. Wouldn't we assume that automatically it gets,
like what are you going to do, gather it into a bucket?
Yeah, I don't understand that. Right. I agree with you, I agree
with you.
Like how are you
not מפקיר mafkir it, like I really say no? No, there are
cases where it's taken for granted you're מפקיר. mafkir. Why the גמרא
Gemara you don't have to do an act of being מפקיר, mafkir,
that is true. Why the גמרא Gemara does not assume that to
be the case by the water, I don't know.
Okay, now, we're going to get to exactly those types of cases
right now.
So now the משנה Mishnah says, so we have the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma of the משנה Mishnah that we're going to find out
in a minute is רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, that says your pitcher
broke in the רשות הרבים reshus harabim. and somebody tripped on the
water or tripped on the shards, you're going to be חייב. chayav
And רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says you're only חייב chayav. if you
intentionally or intentional. So the question is what does intentional mean? And
the real question that the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to ask is pretty
much exactly what Michael was asking, which is: One minute, why when
my pitcher broke am I חייב? chayav Maybe that maybe it was
all maybe it was an אונס, onus. it was an accident, maybe
I didn't have time to remove the shards. And if I make
a בור bor out of by אונס, onus I'm not responsible for
it, right? I presumably at least need a certain degree of negligence
to be digging that בור, bor to be creating that hazard. So
that's exactly what we are going to look at. Let's take a
look. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara, says like this: רבי יהודה אומר
במתכוין חייב, Rebbi Yehuda omer b'miskaven chayav, only if you intended are
you חייב chayav for if somebody trips over your water or your
shards. היכי דמי מתכוין? Heichi dami miskaven? What's meant by מתכוין? miskaven?
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, במתכוין להורידה למטה מכתפו. b'miskaven l'horida l'mata mikseifo.
What you're intent, you're not intending to break it. I mean man,
then you're really like a רשע, rasha, you're breaking and creating an
intentional hazard in רשות הרבים. reshut harabim, No, you're just intending to
take it off of your shoulder and then it slips out of
your hand and it breaks. Okay, so that's the thing. But the
point is that at least there was a more of a fault
then if you were not even trying to take it off of
your shoulder. You're just walking with it on your shoulder, it fell
off, that's like an אונס. onus But when you're taking it off,
obviously you know at that moment of transfer you have to be
paying at right that's when accidents happen at that moment of change
in a transfer. So then there's a certain degree of negligence. Okay,
so what that's saying is for רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda he's saying
you need to have some negligence in creating the בור. bor If
it's a total אונס onus, you're פטור. patur But that would sound
like according to the תנא קמא Tana Kamma even a total אונס
onus. you're חייב. chayav. So that's what the גמרא Gemara asks. So
the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה אביי Amlei Abaye one minute, מכלל
דמחייב רבי מאיר אפילו נפשרה, Mikhall demachayev Reb Meir afilu nifshara, and
you would say רבי מאיר Reb Meir would say you're חייב chayav
even if like the the pitcher sort of like melted in your
hand? Like just sort of collapsed, fell apart? Like an אונס, onus.
right? So אמר ליה אין, Amlei In, yes, מחייב הוה רבי מאיר
אפילו אזנו בידו. mechayev hava Reb Meir afilu ozno beyado. It's a
great image. There you are you're holding on to the ear of
the you know of the pitcher and then the whole pitcher collapses
and you're left holding the ear. Yes, you're חייב chayav even if
you were an אונס. onus. It's your בור. bor Okay.
אמאי, Amai, says the גמרא, Gemara אונס הוא? onush hu? Why? You're
totally blameless. It's an accident. You have no negligence at all. ואונס
רחמנא פטריה. Ve'onus rachmana patrei. And the תורה Torah exempted somebody with
אונס. onus דכתיב Dikh'tiv ולנערה לא
תעשה דבר. velana'ara lo ta'aseh davar. This is a woman who's raped
and it says don't do anything to the woman who was raped,
she's not to blame it was the rapist. Of course you know
for us this is like
obvious but in the ancient world and even today you know you
hear in Middle East or whatever you know it's not like the
woman who's raped she's the one that's blamed like she brings shame
on the family. The תורה Torah is very radical. The תורה Torah
says: No, she was blameless, you know? So that's telling you that
if somebody is blameless they can't be held responsible. וכי תימא Vekhi
tima now lest you say הני מילי בבקטלא. hani milei in'ktala. That's
when it comes to a capital crime. Like maybe when it comes
to an issue of a crime if you're blameless you can't be
prosecuted. אבל עניני נזיקין חייב. Aval inyanei nezikin chayav. Maybe you're חייב
chayav. by נזיקין. nezikin. Now let's just pause for a moment and
say that is that crazy? Why should I be חייב chayav if
I'm blameless? But maybe not. Maybe there's an idea of strict liability,
right? At the end of the day, my thing, my water caused
you to trip and be hurt. Why should you be the one
to lose out? It was my water that did it, let me
be the one to lose out! Right? I said that wrong way.
Whatever. The guy who's hurt says why should I be the one
to lose out, it's your water that did it, you should be
the one to pay for it. Right? Sometimes you know there's a
benefit to society of having rules of strict liability. And by the
way, we have this by אדם המזיק. Adam Hamazik. Right? אדם מועד
לעולם, Adam muad le'olam, putting aside תוספות Tosfos who says it doesn't
mean it. Okay, אדם מועד לעולם Adam muad le'olam means whenever I
do it I pay for it even if I'm blameless. So maybe
the same is true by a בור. bor, Maybe even though I'm
blameless maybe that's yeah רבי מאיר Reb Meir says your בור bor
you're חייב. chayav Okay you don't need any negligence. You are the
one who made the בור. bor Okay? So if you were to
say that והתניא vatanya but you can't say that 'cause we teach
in a ברייתא brayta
נשברו כדו ולא סילקו נפלו גמלו ולא העמידו. Nishberu kado velo silkó
naflo gemalo velo he'emidó. If your pitcher broke and you didn't remove
it or your camel fell down and you didn't make it get
to stand up. רבי מאיר מחייב בהזיקן וחכמים אומרים פטור בדיני אדם
וחייב בדיני שמים. Reb Meir mechayev behezikan vechachamim omrim patur bedinei adam
vechayav bedinei shamayim. רבי מאיר Reb Meir says you're חייב chayav. and
the חכמים chachamim say you're פטור בדיני אדם וחייב בדיני שמים. patur
bedinei adam vechayav bedinei shamayim. So that's like the case in the
משנה. Mishnah. Your pitcher broke, we had a nice example of your
camel. רבי מאיר Reb Meir says you're חייב chayav, the חכמים chachamim
say you're פטור. patur. Now maybe that's a case of אונס. onus
How do you how does that prove to you whether we're talking
about a case of אונס onus or not? Let's look at the
next because we have two other cases that bracket it.
ומודים חכמים לרבי מאיר Umodim chachamim leReb Meir דאבנו סכינו ומשאו de'avne
sakino umas'o your again that
stones knife and bundle שהניחם בראש הגג shehinicham berosh hagag you put
it at the top of your roof ונפלו ברוח מצויה venafelu beruach
metzuya they fell in an expected wind a common wind והזיקו vehiziku
and they damage שהוא חייב shehu chayav that you are חייב. chayav.
So in a case in רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. So they on
the one hand everybody agrees that you're חייב chayav when there's negligence,
right? רוח מצויה ruach metzuya is the classic definition of negligence. So
everybody agrees you're חייב chayav, when you're negligent. How about רבי מאיר
Reb Meir what what would he say? ומודה רבי מאיר לרבנן Umode
Reb Meir lerabbanan and רבי מאיר Reb Meir would agree to the
רבנן rabbanan that you're exempt דמעלה קנקניו לגג dema'ala kankanimo hagag let's
say you put your your your pitchers on the rooftop or whatever
those קנקנים kankanim are not pitchers what are those called anyway whatever
doesn't matter a bottle you put your bottles on the rooftop על
מנת לנגבן amnas lenagvan to dry them out ונפלו ברוח שאינה מצויה
venafelu beruach she'eina metzuya and they fell in an unexpected wind והזיקו
vehiziku and they did damage שהוא פטור shehu patur that you're exempt.
So look at this this ברייתא brayta basically is a great ברייתא.
brayta. It situates the debate between the two poles. Everybody agrees if
it's רוח מצויה ruach metzuya meaning you're negligent you're חייב. chayav Everybody
agrees if it's רוח שאינה מצויה ruach she'eina metzuya you're אונס ones.
you're פטור. patur. They're debating when your thing you know broke when
your pitcher broke which presumably means we see the case of your
pitcher breaking as a middle case as quasi-negligence or questionable which line
do you put it over. Do you put it on the negligent
side of the line or on the אונס ones side of the
line? So that's the case they're debating. So you cannot Say that
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says you're חייב chayav. for a בור bor
that's made באונס. be'ones. Okay, here it's clear that you're only חייב
chayav, for רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir in a middle case. The debate
is a middle case. So this is going to help us understand
what the debate is. So let's take a look.
What it says נשברה כדו ולא סילקה, nishberah kado ve-lo silkah, I
mean, it means like after a reasonable amount of time.
But like how much time? Well, we're yes, I'm going to get
back to that. Okay, I promise you, I'm going to get back
to that. Okay. By the way, I should also point out, and
I don't want to complicate this, but I would just point out
as a footnote that a person could have made the difference and
said in the case of not picking up your pitcher or not
picking up your camel, we're dealing with a case of בור, bor
right? I didn't pick it up and somebody tripped on it. Whereas
the case of something that's falling from the rooftop and does damage,
right? That might have been a different type of thing. That might
have been an אש esh or something like that. But let's bracket
that. The גמרא's Gemara not going there. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
understands that we situate the debate of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and
the חכמים Chachamim about the pitcher and the camel between the two
poles. All right. So let's take a look. So what's the debate
going to be about? אלא אמר אביי, Ela amar Abaye, so אביי
Abaye says, בתרתי פליגי. bitartei peligi. It's debate two cases. פליגי בשעת
נפילה, peligi be-sha'at nefilah, when the thing is falling, you're falling like,
you know, the pitcher fell out of your hand, okay, ופליגי לאחר
נפילה. u-peligi le-achar nefilah. And then it damaged something in its fall.
ופליגי לאחר נפילה, u-peligi le-achar nefilah, after it fell and somebody slipped
on it. Okay. פליגי בשעת נפילה. peligi be-sha'at nefilah. Now what's the
question about when it at the moment that it fell? I tripped,
the pitcher fell out of my hand and it hit Michael. What's
the question? So that's the question of בנתקל פושע, be-nitkal poshea, whether
tripping is considered to be negligent or not. Okay. מר סבר נתקל
פושע mar savar nitkal poshea ומר סבר נתקל לאו פושע. u-mar savar
nitkal lav poshea. One says it is negligent and the other says
it's not negligent. So basically what the גמרא Gemara says is, right?
Here you have the case of רוח מצויה ruach metzuyah which is
פשיעה, peshi'ah. which is the definition of פשיעה. peshi'ah. Oh, do I
have it on top? Yes. Oh, look at that. Okay. Except there
I used the גניבה ואבידה, gneivah va-aveidah, but I'll take off the
גניבה ואבידה gneivah va-aveidah as part. Okay, excellent. Okay. So you have
רוח מצויה ruach metzuyah which is full פשיעה. peshi'ah You have אינה
מצויה, eina metzuyah,
okay, which is considered to be אונס. ones? So those are two
extremes. So here everybody agrees when it's fell by רוח מצויה, ruach
metzuyah, everybody agrees you're פטור. patur. Here when it fell off the
rooftop by a רוח מצויה, ruach metzuyah, everybody agrees you're חייב. chayav.
Okay. And the debate is, right? What happens in the case of
נתקל? nitkal, נתקל, nitkal a case of when you trip, is somewhere
in the middle of those two extremes. You tripped over your own
two feet and your pitcher fell down. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara
seems to include, one minute, the גמרא Gemara seems to include in
the נתקל nitkal. if we're still dealing with נתכוון להורידה, nitkaven le-horidah,
the גמרא Gemara. seems to include in the נתקל nitkal not just
tripping over my own two feet, but you know, transferring a pitcher
and it slipping out of my hand. Those types of things where
you say like, you know, we all know those types of things
at home, right? You're passing something and it falls and it spills
or whatever. Like was it an accident or were you not being
careful? Right? It's a little bit of both. Okay. So those types
of things of נתקל, nitkal either slipping on your own two feet,
the thing slipping out of your hand or whatever, is between those
two extremes. So the question is where do you draw the line?
So רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir draws the line here,
right? רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says it's on this side of פשיעה
peshiah and you're חייב, chayav. right? And you know, and רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda draws the line here and he says נתקל nitkal is
on that side, right? And you're going to be פטור. patur? Okay.
So you know, it's always the question: are they debating how negligent
the person is or where to draw the line? All right. But
either way, the point is, is that the debate is in the
case of slipping. That's one debate. Everybody agrees if you're an אונס
ones, you're פטור, patur. if you're a פושע poshea you're חייב. chayav
The question is the pitcher slipped out of your hand. You tripped
over your own two feet. Are you פושע poshea or are you
אונס? ones. Which side of the line does it fall on? Okay.
That's the debate. מר סבר נתקל פושע הוא mar savar nitkal poshea
hu ומר סבר נתקל לאו פושע הוא. u-mar savar nitkal lav poshea
hu. Notice it doesn't say אונס, ones it says לאו פושע, lav
poshea, right? Because there's obviously a you know, you're not enough negligent.
There's a there is a certain degree of carelessness, but not enough
to make you a פושע. poshea. Okay. You're not פושע. poshea. So
that's the debate. Okay. ופליגי, u-peligi, that's debate number one. Now why
wouldn't we just have ended there? That would have explained everything very
nicely. But אביי Abaye complicates it by saying there's another level of
the debate as well. Okay. נתקל לאו פושע. nitkal lav poshea. פליגי
לאחר נפילה, peligi le-achar nefilah, now they also debate after it fell
and now you have your broken shards and you haven't picked them
up.
במפקיר נזקיו. bi-mafkir nizakav. We assume that after it fell, you're just
sort of like, 'Ah, that's it. I'm not going to bother with
it. I'm going to... you know, what, I'm going to pick up
my broken shards and my spilled water?' Like this is what Michael
was saying. You just it's presumed that you're just מפקיר mafkir it.
All right. You מפקיר mafkir it after it broke, but you מפקיר
mafkir it after it broke and then somebody slips on it, are
you חייב chayav, now?
מר סבר... mar savar... מר סבר מפקיר נזקיו, Mar savar mafkir nizakav,
I will discuss it. Yes, it might be. מר סבר מפקיר נזקיו
חייב, Mar savar mafkir nizakav chayav, you're חייב, chayav. and מר סבר
פטור. mar savar patur. One says you're פטור. patur. Now, I need
to pause to explain to you two ways of understanding
מפקיר נזקיו, mafkir nizakav, which is going to be made explicit in
the גמרא Gemara in a minute. Okay. There is one scenario which
is that basically,
let's say this thing fell out of my hands out of negligence,
okay. We agree that it was negligent, it fell out of my
hands. And now I am going to say like, oh, but you
know what, at this point on I am
basically, let me see how I would say this.
Okay, I'm sorry, let's start the other way. Let's start about what
would be the story if I was not מפקיר mafkir it. If
I was not מפקיר mafkir it, so and it fell out of
my hands, certainly if it was פושע poshea and it remains mine,
I'm חייב chayav. if somebody trips on it. Let's say it fell
out of my hands באונס be'ones and it's there and I wasn't
פושע. poshea. Fine, no fault. And if somebody got tripped on it
right away in the next two seconds I also would be blameless.
But if I kept ownership of the object, let's say I don't
know my knife, not my thing that's now little shards, my knife
fell out of my hands, it was a total complete accident, for
the first moment that it fell and the first few seconds afterwards
I'm exempt. But afterwards, if I just leave my knife there and
do nothing, I'm negligent and I'm חייב. chayav. It's my knife, I
should go ahead and pick it up and remove it. And if
I have a chance to remove it and I don't remove it,
then I'm חייב, chayav. right? So we can all understand that. Even
if it fell באונס, be'ones, if I retain ownership and it's still
mine and I have the opportunity to remove it and I didn't,
then my leaving it there is negligence. Okay. So that's a case
of everyone with me here?
Okay, so that's a case of נפילת אונס. nefilat ones. Okay, it
fell באונס. be'ones. So from the moment this falls till you have
the chance to pick it up, here you've got a chance to
pick it up. You have a chance to pick it up. Okay.
So until you have a chance to pick it up, you're going
to be פטור. patur Now you have a chance to pick it
up. Okay. So now it goes like this: If you still own
it,
you're חייב.
chayav Depends on what, right? בור bor or אדם adam or כלים,
kelim, right?
Doesn't matter. You have a chance to pick it up, you own
it, you're supposed to remove it, you're חייב. chayav. Okay, but let's
say it fell out of your hands באונס, be'ones, okay and then
you said forget it, I'm מפקיר, mafkir, I don't need it, I'm
leaving it, okay. My stupid rock, I don't know what I was
doing carrying the rock anyway, okay, I don't want it, okay. So
then, you didn't make the בור bor בפשיעה. be'pshia. The בור bor,
was made באונס. be'ones. And now, if you are מפקיר mafkir it
before you had a chance to pick it up,
you had no responsibility to remove it, okay. So therefore if you're
מפקיר mafkir in that case then you're going to be פטור. patur
Okay. So you're פטור patur, here because you're not to blame. Here
you're חייב chayav because you own it and you could remove it.
But if you were מפקיר mafkir it after it fell and it
didn't fall due to your blame, you're going to be exempt, okay.
So that's the case that everybody agrees to.
מפקיר נזקיו לאחר נפילת אונס mafkir nizakav achar nefilat ones everybody agrees
that
in that
case you're going to be פטור. patur, Okay, so
that's
what's been debated. Would you wait? Okay, we are going to get
to it, trust me. That's that case. Now let's say it was
נפילת פשיעה. nefilat pshia. Okay, so it fell בפשיעה. be'pshia. Okay, so
you're פושע. poshea. So here you are, you're חייב, chayav because the
בור bor was made בפשיעה. be'pshia. Okay, now you have a chance
to remove it, I mean it really shouldn't matter, you're פושע poshea
all along, so you should say whether you're מפקיר mafkir or you're
not מפקיר, mafkir, you should say you're חייב. chayav. You made the
בור, bor. right? You made the בור bor. בפשיעה, be'pshia, who cares
if now you own it or not. When I dig a בור
bor in רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, I don't own it. I made
it. Okay, so if you made it whether now you continue to
own it or don't continue to own it, you should be חייב.
chayav So logically we should say מפקיר נזקיו לאחר נפילת פשיעה mafkir
nizakav achar nefilat pshia you
should be you should be חייב. chayav That's what should be logical,
okay. So
we said that the debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was whether when you fell you're considered to be
פושע poshea or אונס. ones Yes, everybody with me? So you could
have said that. said that if they're also debating a case of
מפקיר, mafkir, you're מפקיר mafkir after it fell, it's really just an
extension of the initial debate. If you were an אונס ones. when
it originally got made and then you were מפקיר mafkir it, then
you continue to be פטור. patur, If you were a פושע poshea
when it originally fell and you were מפקיר mafkir it, then it
doesn't matter, you continue to be חייב. chayav That will be an
approach of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan in a minute, that it's really
not two debates, it's really all one debate, whether you were an
אונס ones. or a פושע, poshea, okay? But what
what רבא Rava is saying or אביי Abaye is saying is, אביי
Abaye is complicating the matters as if this wasn't complicated enough. אביי
Abaye is complicating the matters and אביי Abaye is saying
even if you were negligent when it fell, if you're מפקיר mafkir
it according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda you're פטור. patur Why? That's
crazy. I made it, if I dug a well and I מפקיר,
mafkir, would I be פטור? patur And the answer is or I
didn't own it to begin with, I dug a well in רשות
הרבים. reshus harabbim And the answer is according to this, yes. There's
an opinion that says that the only time that תורה Torah said
you're obligated for digging a well is if you dig it in
your domain, right at the edge of רשות הרבים, reshus ha-rabim so
it's a hazard. But if you there's it's totally ironic. If you
dig a well in the middle of a רשות הרבים reshut ha'rabim
where it's you don't own it, you're פטור. patur, That understands that
the obligation of a בור bor, is a type of a ממון
המזיק. mamon hamazik. It's not just that you created a hazard, it's
actually a type of a ממון המזיק. mamon hamazik. So this is
an opinion that's saying that אביי Abaye is saying number one they
debate when it fell if you're פושע poshea or you're אונס. ones.
Okay, and what happens if somebody got damaged exactly at that moment
in the few seconds while it was falling or the few seconds
after it fell. Then we have to decide are you a פושע
poshea or an אונס. ones. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you're a
פושע poshea and and
and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you're not פושע. poshea. But then
we have to say even if you were negligent, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda would exempt you if you were מפקיר mafkir because רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says you're not חייב chayav. on a בור bor, that
you don't own. Okay, which is like totally a completely unrelated debate
and seems very arbitrary. So let's read that, okay?
מר סבר נתקא פושע, Mar savar nitka poshea, we're going to read
it again, ומר סבר נתקא לאו פושע. umar savar nitka lav poshea.
So if somebody got damaged immediately as it was falling or in
the few seconds after it fell, then that's the debate of whether
you're negligent or not negligent. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you are
negligent and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you are not. Okay please
ופליגי לאחר נפילה, upligi leachar nefila, they also debate after it fell
and here what's missing but what the גמרא Gemara will clarify in
a minute means even if it fell with negligence, they debate after
it fell דמפקיר נזיקיו. de-mafkir nezikov. מר סבר מפקיר נזיקיו חייב, Mar
savar mafkir nezikov chayav, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says I don't care
that you're מפקיר נזיקיו, mafkir nezikov, if it fell with negligence you're
going to be חייב. chayav ומר
סבר Umar savar and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says פטור. patur. No,
even if it fell with negligence, if you don't own it anymore,
you're פטור patur. on a בור bor. that you don't own, okay?
So מר Mar says וממאי, umimay, how do you know this? מדקתני
תרתי Midisani tarti because the משנה Mishnah says two cases. הוחלק אחד
במים או שלקה בחרסית. Huchlak echad bemayim o shelaka becharisis. You slipped
on the water or you got yourself hurt on the shard. היינו
הך, Hainu hach, why did it have to give both scenarios? I
mean give me a break, whatever, it's just a little bit but
okay, a little you know illustrating but okay, a little color. אלא
לאו הכי קאמר Ella lav hachi ka-amar to give you two cases.
הוחלק אחד במים בשעת נפילה, Huchlak echad bemayim beshas nefila, you slipped
while it was falling. Now that's a little funny, how do you
slip while the water's falling? Which basically means that you have to
understand that while it's falling means as it's falling and in the
few moments after when you don't yet have a chance to remove
it. So then your falls is all defined by that initial falling,
not that oh you should have removed it. Okay? So one scenario
is somebody got damaged in the first few seconds afterwards and therefore
it's a debate of whether you were negligent when it got when
it broke or were you not negligent, is it your בור bor
or not your בור, bor? right? If there so that's scenario number
one. בשעת beshas or minute הוחלק אחד
במים בשעת נפילה או שלקה בחרסית לאחר נפילה. huchlak echad bemayim beshas
nefila o shelaka becharisis leachar nefila. Or you got the guy got
damaged in the shard after you had a chance to remove it.
Now why are you debating after you had a chance to remove
it? So you could have said it's an extension of the same
debate. Okay? But no, what he is saying is even if like
it's a different scenario, which is such a hard read of the
גמרא. Gemara Even if it was a case where we can concede
that it fell with negligence, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would still say
you're exempt because it's no longer a בור bor that you own.
Yes?
Anybody I mean water you can't clean up? Right. So there's no
distinguishing between
something that's possible...
Oh, that's an interesting point. Like if it would really not be
possible, like I don't know why it's not possible, you know, you
could get a towel, get a mop or whatever, but if it's
really not possible then you're right. Then if you were if you
were not negligent when it fell then there's no negligence now because
there's nothing you can't put a triangle, you can't stand there warn
people. If it's really true that there's no negligence now, then that
would be then you'd be continue to be exempt. Okay, so גמרא
Gemara says like this, ומדימא umidima how ומדמתניתין בתרתי, u-mid-masnis bi-tarti, since
our משנה Mishnah talked about two cases, ברייתא נמי בתרתי. braisa nami
bi-tarti. The ברייתא braisa which, remember, talked about the pitcher and the
camel, okay, is also talking about both scenarios. Now why we don't
say the pitcher is one and the camel is another is interesting.
We're going to say both the pitcher and the camel of the
ברייתא braisa are talking about both scenarios, when it's falling and after
it fell. Okay, ברייתא נמי
בתרתי. braisa nami bi-tarti.
בשלמא כדא, bishlama kadda, so by the case of the pitcher, I
can get both scenarios. משכחת לה, meshkachas lah, או בשעת נפילה, o
be-sha’as nefilah, either it fell, it fell out of your hands, you
tripped, it fell when you were taking it off your shoulder, so
that's one debate: were you negligent or not? רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says you were negligent, that that's considered negligence, and רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says it isn't. או לאחר נפילה, o le-achar nefilah, or it's
after it fell and then you were מפקיר mafkir it and you
didn't clean it up, okay, whereas even if you were negligent, רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you're exempt because you have to own the
בור. bor So that I get. אלא גמלא, ela gamla, but your
camel, בשלמא לאחר נפילה משכחת לה, bishlama le-achar nefilah meshkachas lah, I
get the scenario of the camel of after it fell, במפקיר נבלתו,
be-mafkir nivelaso, which is funny. Your camel fell and it like, because
why are you being מפקיר mafkir your camel? Because it fell and
it died and you're מפקיר mafkir the carcass. Even then, why are
you מפקיר mafkir the carcass? Presumably it's worth some good money. Turn
it into dog meat or something, use it for leather. Anyway, it's
a very funny scenario. Anyway, that I can get. Okay, so even
though you were negligent, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you're exempt because
you don't own the בור. bor אלא בשעת נפילה היכי משכחת לה?
ela be-sha’as nefilah heichi meshkachas lah? How about while it's falling? Now,
why is that? What's the big problem? The problem is not that
I can't understand that a camel can fall on someone and hurt
them, but the whole debate was when you trip and when you
slip, are you negligent? Right, when I'm taking it off my shoulder
and it slips out of my hands, am I negligent? When my
camel slips, it's assumed that that's a different discussion. Like, my camel
normally watches where it's going. Animals are very good about that. I'm
not... what am I supposed to do, watch that the camel isn't
stepping in a puddle? So if the camel actually slips, presumably that's
an אונס. onus, So how do you have a case of debating
whether it's negligent when the animal slips? It's a good question. Okay,
I told you that story, right, about the case about like when
I was horseback riding with this woman and she like... we saw
these people on these sand buggies and I said, "Oh, that looks
like a lot of fun." She said, "I would never do that."
I said, "Why?" She says, "The sand buggy can go over a
cliff. A horse will never go over a
cliff." Okay, so when a horse... when a camel slips, presumably that's
an אונס. onus, How could you be debating that case? So the
גמרא Gemara's says, okay,
אמר רב אחא, amar Rav Acha, כגון דעברה במיא דרך שרצתא דנהרא.
kegon de-avra be-maya derech shartzata de-nahara. You were going through water, basically,
where the way רש"י Rashi explains this is like water flooded the
street and you were crossing across the water that was flooding the
street. So you were negligent taking your camel across that water. So
the גמרא Gemara says, okay, but remember, it's a debate whether you're
negligent or not. היכי דמי? heichi dami? What's the case? אי דאיכא
דרכא אחרינא, ei de-ika darcha achrina, if you could go around, detour,
פושע הוא, poshea hu, then everybody should agree you're negligent by going
through the water. אי דליכא דרכא אחרינא, ei de-leika darcha achrina, if
you're stuck in the middle of a רשות הרבים reshut ha'rabim, and
there's no choice but to go through the water, אונס הוא. ones
hu. So you had no choice. So okay, still, what's the scenario
where they could be debating whether you're negligent when your camel falls
down? אלא משכחת לה דאיתקל, ela meshkachas lah de-is-kal, you tripped over
your own two feet, ואיתקל ביה גמלא, ve-is-kal bei gamla, and then
your camel tripped on you. Now it's not you tripped and you
knocked over your camel; that would be a pretty good trip. But
in fact, you tripped and fell on the ground and then your
camel tripped on top of you. It's all because of your initial
negligence. So it's the same debate of you're negligent.
Okay, the least of your problems is going to be...
Exactly, you probably have a broken back. Anyway, okay, so because the
גמרא Gemara needed to read both cases both ways, we had this
discrepancy, but bottom line is, what אביי Abaye saying is, look, the
basic debate of the משנה, Mishnah, I think we could agree, is
when something falls out of your hand, are you negligent or not?
And that would determine the period
immediately following the falling out of your hand before you have a
chance to pick it up. Now, if you were not negligent, nevertheless,
if you still own it and have a chance to pick it
up afterwards, you're going to be חייב chayav after that moment. Okay,
but one debate is, are you negligent when it falls? אביי Abaye
introduces a completely really conceptually completely unrelated debate that even if you
are negligent, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say you're exempt if you
no longer own it. Why is that? You only are חייב chayav.
for a בור bor that you own. And now the גמרא's Gemara,
going to read that into the משנה. Mishnah. Let's take a look.
גמרא Gemara says like
this, okay, מפקיר נזקו במאי מתכוין איכא? mafkir nizko be-mai miskavein ika?
We get how you read the משנה Mishnah when רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says only if you're מתכוין, miskavein, means only if you're trying
to move it off your shoulder and then it slips out of
your hand, then you're
negligent, okay. Or excuse me, actually no, now what we're saying is
that according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda only if you're intending to
break it, right, or but if you're... it's a normal slipping, you're
actually not negligent. That would actually be the case of the first
part of the משנה. Mishnah. That רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*
says a normal slipping is negligent and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi
Yehuda* says no, only like an intentional breaking, you know, only then
would you be חייב chayav. *chayav*. That explains the first case. But
how about where do you read this מתכוין *mitkavein* issue into the
question of whether you're when you מפקיר mafkir *mafkir* it after it
fell? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, what מתכוין איכא *mitkavein ika*?
So אמר רב יוסף *Amar Rav Yosef*, במתכוין לזכות בחרסיה *b'mitkavein lizkot
b'charaseha*. וכן אמר רב אשי *V'chen amar Rav Ashi*, במתכוין לזכות בחרסיה
*b'mitkavein lizkot b'charaseha*. What this מתכוין *mitkavein* means is something else. It
broke with negligence and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehuda* is saying
if you want to intentionally want to maintain ownership over it and
it remains yours, then you're going to be חייב chayav *chayav*. But
if you no longer want to maintain ownership, and it sounds like
the default is that you won't, you have to intentionally want to
maintain ownership. If you no longer want to maintain ownership, then you
don't own it, okay? So we now have two different debates going
on in the משנה mishna *Mishnah*. One is when it falls. The
תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* says you're negligent, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
*Rabbi Yehuda* says no, only like an intentional breaking, only then would
you be חייב chayav *chayav*. And then the other debate is even
when it fell with negligence, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says
you're only going to be חייב chayav *chayav* if you continue to
own it. If you don't continue to own it, you're going to
be פטור patur. *patur*. You're only חייב chayav *chayav* for a בור
bor? *bor* that you own. Okay, that's a little complicated because the
second debate really has nothing to do with the first one. The
next approach will be an easier one. Let's take a look. Yes.
So the classic בור bor? *bor* is you dig a hole in
רשות הרבים reshut ha'rabim *reshut harabbim*. Right. Nobody would own that.
Right. So according to this, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* would
say you're not חייב chayav, *chayav* for a בור bor *bor* in
רשות הרבים reshut ha'rabim *reshut harabbim*. You're only חייב chayav *chayav* for
a בור bor, *bor* you dig right at the edge of רשות
הרבים reshut ha'rabim *reshut harabbim* that you own. Okay, it's completely bizarre,
but he says the basic חיוב
*chiyuv* for a בור bor? *bor* is ממון המזיק *mamon hamazik*, not
a hazard.
Okay. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: Okay,
רבי אלעזר אומר *Rabbi Elazar omer*. Now that's אביי Abaye *Abaye*. He
says they debate when it fell and after it fell. Two different
debates. רבי אלעזר אומר בשעת נפילה מחלוקת *Rabbi Elazar omer bishas nefila
machloket*. They debate when it fell. So that, okay, when it fell,
that's a nice explanation. Only you know the immediate question of are
you פושע poshea *posheia* or not? That's, let's make it nice and
simple, one issue. At the time it fell and immediately afterwards, are
you פושע poshea *posheia* or not? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
אבל לאחר נפילה מאי *aval l'achar nefila mai*? But what so what
is רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* saying after it fell? דבי הכל פטור
patur. *di'vei ha-kol patur*, everybody would say that you're exempt? ואיכא רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir דמחייב *ve'ika Rabbi Meir de'mechayev*. Where does רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* say you're חייב chayav *chayav*? Because if you
go back to the ברייתא braita. *brayta*, the ברייתא braita. *brayta* says
נפל כדו ולא העמידה vlo heemida, *nafal kado v'lo he'emida*, נפל גמלו
ולא העמידו *nafal gemalo v'lo he'emido*. So the ברייתא braita *brayta* is
talking about a case where you had a chance to pick it
up and you didn't pick it up, right? The ברייתא *brayta* isn't
saying at the moment it fell are you חייב chayav *chayav*. The
ברייתא *brayta* is saying there's a debate about when you had the
opportunity to pick it up. So that's considered after it fell, so
that has to be part of the debate, okay? So you can't
say that everybody would say you're פטור patur *patur* because רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says if you didn't stand up your camel,
you're going to be חייב chayav *chayav*. אלא מאי דבי הכל חייב
chayav *ela mai di'vei ha-kol chayav*? So you want to say the
opposite? After it fell everybody says you're חייב chayav *chayav* because you
should have picked it up? ואיכא רבנן rabbanan דפטרי *ve'ika rabanan de'patrei*.
But in the same case with the camel that you didn't pick
up, the Rabbis say you're פטור patur. *patur*. So meaning, this point
tells you why אביי Abaye *Abaye* said there are two debates, because
the ברייתא *brayta* emphasizes that the problem was after it fell, you
didn't pick it up. So you can't say they only debate at
the time it fell because the ברייתא *brayta* makes it clear that
part of the debate is after it fell, okay? אלא מאי בשעת
נפילה אף בשעת נפילה *ela mai bishas nefila af bishas nefila*. דקמשמע
לן כאביי *dekamashlan k'Abaye*, fine, רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* doesn't mean anything
different than אביי *Abaye*. He means not only do they debate after
it fell, which is clear in the ברייתא *brayta* because the ברייתא
*brayta* says you didn't pick it up, which means that's the problem.
They're also debating when it fell, and that's the משנה mishna, *Mishnah*,
and that's like אביי *Abaye*. They're debating both when it fell and
after it fell, and presumably two separate debates: one whether you're פושע
poshea, *posheia*, and the other whether you need to continue to own
the בור bor. *bor*. Okay, so that is רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar*
like אביי *Abaye*. But now we're going to get what's probably the
most simplest explanation I think, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan אמר *Rabbi Yochanan
amar*, who basically makes it about one debate. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan.
*Rabbi Yochanan* says לאחר נפילה מחלוקת *l'achar nefila machloket*. They debate after
it fell. That's the ברייתא *brayta*, you didn't pick up your camel,
you didn't pick up your pitcher. They're debating what's the story after
it fell.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one minute, אבל בשעת נפילה מאי
*aval bishas nefila mai*? What would you say when it fell? דבי
הכל פטור pattur *di'vei ha-kol patur*, everybody would agree at the moment
of falling it's פטור pattur, *patur*, that you're an אונס onus *oness*
at the moment of falling? והא דקאמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan לקמן
*vehamide'ka'amar Rabbi Yochanan l'kaman*. Now, that's not a problem in terms of
explaining the ברייתא *brayta* and the משנה mishna, *Mishnah*. The ברייתא *brayta*
and משנה mishna *Mishnah* could easily be explained that the debate is,
everybody agreed when it fell out of your hand you're an אונס
onus, *oness*. That, let's stop a minute and appreciate, that would be
a nice good explanation of the ברייתא *brayta* and the משנה mishna
*Mishnah*. Remember before the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said that according to רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* even if it dissolved in your hand
you'd be חייב chayav *chayav* and the גמרא *Gemara* couldn't understand how
you're חייב chayav, *chayav* if it's an אונס ones *oness*? Maybe the
whole debate is not at the moment it fell. The moment it
fell everybody agrees you're an אונס ones *oness*. Everybody agrees you're פטור.
pattur, The question is what's your responsibility afterwards? רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says afterwards you got to pick it up, maybe even after you
were מפקיר mafkir. it. It's your thing, you got to pick it
up, once you've had a chance to pick it up you're חייב.
chayav. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. says no, if at the moment
itself you're פטור pattur, you remain פטור, pattur especially if you were
מפקיר. mafkir That would have been a nice debate, maybe the whole
debate is after it fell. When it fell you were פטור, after
it fell we're debating what degree of responsibility you have. So that
would be a great read of the משנה mishna and the ברייתא.
The only problem is רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan himself says something that
excludes that as the position of
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan והא מדקאמר רבי יוחנן לקמן veha mideka-amar Rabbi
Yochanan lekamman and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, himself said לא תימא מתניתין
רבי מאיר היא דאמר נתקל פושע. lo tema matnitin Rabbi Meir hi
de-amar nitkal poshea. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir dealing with a different משנה,
mishna not our משנה, mishna a later משנה mishna says don't think
that later משנה mishna is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says נתקל
פושע. nitkal poshea That shows that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan understands that
part of the debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the חכמים
chachamim is whether you're negligent or not when you trip. מכלל דרבי
מאיר מחייב, mikhlal de-Rabbi Meir mechayev, you see that רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says that at the moment itself you're חייב chayav because you
are negligent. אלא מאי דכולי עלמא מחייב ella mai de-koli alma mechayev
so you'll say the opposite, maybe everybody agrees that when it fell
you are negligent. That again they're not debating when it fell cause
you're always פטור, they're not debating when it fell cause you're always
negligent. You can't say that. Same point. והא מדקאמר רבי מאיר לקמן
לא תימא מתניתין רבי מאיר היא דאמר נתקל פושע הוא, veha mideka-amar
Rabbi Meir lekamman lo tema matnitin Rabbi Meir hi de-amar nitkal poshea
hu, same point. Since רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says later, oh that
משנה Mishnah: over there isn't רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says נתקל
פושע nitkal poshea. shows that he thinks that that question of tripping,
are you פושע poshea or not, is a debate between רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir and the חכמים. chachamim. מכלל דפטרי רבנן mikhlal de-pateri rabanan
clearly
the rabbis say that at the time it fell you're exempt. So
clearly רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir from his own statement later makes it
clear that he understands that the debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
and the חכמים chachamim is also a debate of whether you're negligent
or not. So let's,
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, sorry רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan right. So
let's just stop a minute and appreciate.
At the time it's falling that could be a debate of whether
you're negligent or not when it fell, is נתקל פושע. nitkal poshea,
That's one way of framing the debate. It's clear from what רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says later on that that's how he understands the
debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda or
at least one way he understands this. Because he says, you know,
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds נתקל פושע, nitkal poshea, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda: holds it's not, etc. That's one way of understanding the debate.
Another way of understanding the debate is let's totally focus after it
fell. Let's assume it fell באונס be-onus and then there's a reasonable
question: if it fell באונס be-onus and now you've had a chance
to pick it up, what's your degree of responsibility? That by the
way could be the ברייתא. It actually could work very well. The
משנה Mishnah could be talking about when it fell, are you פושע
poshea or not, right? But anyway, but let's say so one way
to frame it is that when you're אונס, ones even if you're
אונס, ones do you, are you responsible if you don't pick it
up afterwards? But for so that's two ways of explaining. But if
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan wound up saying both ways, so since he
said that according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir you're like, according to,
so how is he going to sort of synchronize the two? According
to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir you're חייב chayav because you're פושע, poshea
according to the חכמים chachamim you're פטור because you're an אונס oness.
at the time that it fell. So then what's the next part
of the debate if you didn't pick it up, right? So where's
what? מפקיר ניזקיו. mafkir nizo-kav. Well that's going to be so the
next part of the debate really isn't going to be a second
debate. It's really going to be an extension of the first. So
let's just read that. Hold on, get the גמרא in a minute
but let's just read that. אלא says גמרא, הא קא משמע לן
ha kamashma lan when רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, is saying the debate
is after it fell, what he's telling you is דמפקיר ניזקיו דהכא
הוא דפטרי רבנן דאונס הוא. de-mafkir nizo-kav de-hakha hu de-pateri rabanan de-onus
hu. The reason the,
it's a case of מפקיר ניזקיו mafkir nizo-kav and that's why the
rabbis say you're פטור because you're an אונס, because you weren't at
fault to begin with. And since you weren't at fault to begin
with and now you don't own it, that's why you have no
responsibility. That's why if you didn't pick up your camel you have
no responsibility, you didn't pick up your pitcher you have no responsibility,
because you weren't פושע poshea. to begin with and now you don't
own it. אבל מפקיר ניזקיו דעלמא aval mafkir nizo-kav de-alma but if
after it fell with negligence you were מפקיר mafkir it, מחייב, mechayev,
you would be חייב chayav. because that's like digging a בור ברשות
הרבים. bor be-reshut harabim. If you created it with negligence you're חייב.
chayav So that's the easiest way to explain. That's what רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says. Basically,
I don't know if this is going to get too complicated, but
anyway, so here was, here's שעת נפילה shat nefila
and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says חייב chayav and רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says פטור, and that's the case of, that's really sort of
if you want that's like the case of the משנה Mishnah because
that's the case it just says, whatever, the משנה Mishnah doesn't emphasize
you didn't pick it up, the משנה Mishnah just says somebody was
damaged, so that sounds like שעת נפילה. shat nefila. So we say
what is this a debate? This is a debate of whether נתקל
פושע, nitkal poshea, are you considered to be negligent when it fell?
That's שעת נפילה. shat nefila. And then the ברייתא says, right... ולא
העמידה, which means that the problem was, was it was אחר נפילה.
achar nefilah. The problem was that you didn't pick it up. Okay,
and how much do you have a responsibility for picking it up
as well? Okay, and there רבי מאיר says also חייב chayav and
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, says פטור. So what's that second
debate? Okay, so אביי says this second debate is in a case
of פשיעה peshiah, and it's a question that even when you were
negligent, maybe if you don't own it now you're פטור. What a
completely different point that even if you were negligent in making a
בור, bor? if you don't own the בור, bor it's a בור
ברשות הרבים bor b'reshus harabim not a בור ברשותו, bor b'reshuso, you
are מפקיר mafkir and you don't own it, you're going to be
פטור. Completely unrelated debate, which is hard to read in. Okay, what
רבי יוחנן Rebi Yochanan is saying is, no, this is really not
a second debate. It's an extension of the first one. This is
a case of מפקיר נזקיו, mafkir nezikav, okay, which אביי said also,
but according to רבי יוחנן, it's an extension of the debate. If
since you were מפקיר mafkir, it, if it started with פשיעה, peshiah,
you remain חייב. chayav If it started with אונס and now you
don't own it, even after you've had a chance to pick it
up, you remain פטור. It's an extension of this. But that's only
because they're only debating this because it started with a case of
נתקל. nitkal But if it started with a case of פשיעה, peshiah
okay, if you were actually had a case of פשיעה peshiah and
then you were מפקיר, mafkir okay, everybody would say you're going to
be חייב. chayav Okay, it doesn't matter that you don't own it,
you don't need to own it, you need to be at fault.
Okay, so the reason מפקיר mafkir is significant here is because it
removes your ability to be at fault for רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda,
You're אונס here and you didn't own it, so you don't have
a responsibility to pick it up, you remain faultless, right? But if
you started with fault, everybody would agree מפקיר mafkir, won't get you
out of it. Okay, so this debate is really just an extension
of this. And what it's just saying is for רבי יהודה you
will remain פטור as long even if you didn't pick it up
as long as you don't own it. But if you do own
it, right, there're two ways you're going to be חייב chayav for
רבי יהודה: either you own it, okay, here you're not מפקיר, mafkir
okay, if you own it, you're going to be חייב chayav because
then you should pick it up.
That's one scenario. And another scenario is פשיעה peshia, and then מפקיר
mafkir and you're going to be חייב chayav because because of your
original negligence. You need one moment of negligence. Okay, but if it
fell and you were an אונס because we say tripping is an
אונס and then you were מפקיר mafkir it, so you don't have
any responsibility to pick it up, those are the cases within רבי
יהודה that you're going to be פטור. Very nice read of the
two cases. Yes.
Some of these issues involved or were involved when the Congress passed
the Superfund law. Companies would מפקיר mafkir their hazardous waste sites and
they changed the law to go after those companies
even after they were מפקיר mafkir their stuff. Okay, yeah, Jenna.
So for רבי מאיר when he is חייב and saying זהו פושע,
zehu poshea, he doesn't give that window, that leeway window of being
able to pick it up?
Yeah, because you were פושע poshea from the original creating of the
בור. bor? So even if you didn't have a chance to pick
it up, you were at fault at the very stuff is on
the floor to begin with.
Right, but we're still saying it's not intentional?
No, you don't need to be intentional, you just need to be
negligent, right? That's what this whole thing is.
Can you imagine a situation where someone would say even though
you're at fault, right, that creating a בור bor. has to be
intentional creating a בור? bor Yeah,
but but we're not saying that we're saying I mean if I
dug the בור bor. and I didn't have a chance to fill
it up and somebody fell into it I obviously I'd be חייב,
right? So we're saying the same thing if I created it through
negligence.
I'm basically eliminating the difference between פושע and כוונה. kavana.
Yeah, the biggest thing in you know other than let's say חייב
for בושת boshes or whatever it is, you know, it's all really
here about negligence, not about intention, right? That's the dominant thing. Right,
you don't have the three categories, we're just going to read פושע.
Yeah, but that is the dominant principle.
You're right, the Torah talks about
for example making a fire intentionally, making a בור bor intentionally, but
for us it basically becomes an issue of negligence. Okay, so let's
keep on going. So the גמרא says like this, איתמר, itmar, it
was said, okay, מפקיר נזקיו, mafkir nezikav, רבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר, Rabbi
Yochanan v'Rabbi Elazar, חד אמר חייב וחד אמר פטור. chad amar chayav
v'chad amar patur. All right, so now, לימא, leima, so it seems
like what we were just talking about, מאן דמחייב כרבי מאיר ומאן
דפטר כרבנן, man d'mechayev k'Rabbi Meir u'man d'pater k'rabbanan, right, that this
is debate of רבי מאיר and the רבנן whether מפקיר נזקיו mafkir
nezikav you're חייב or not? Okay, so the גמרא says no, אליבא
דרבי מאיר כולי עלמא לא פליגי. aliba d'Rabbi Meir kuli alma lo
pligi. According to רבי מאיר that if you're נתקל פושע, everybody would
agree. That you remain חייב because you had that original פשיעה, even
if you're מפקיר mafkir. it afterwards. כי פליגי אליבא דרבנן. ki p'ligi
aliba de'Rabbanan. That when you're נתקל you're an אונס. Okay. אליבא דרבנן.
aliba de'Rabbanan. מאן דפטר כרבנן, man de'pater ke'Rabbanan, so you originally not
a פושע and now you don't own it, so you remain exempt.
ומאן דמחייב אמר לך, u'man de'mechayev amar lach, and the one that
would say you're חייב when you're מפקיר נזקיו mafkir nezikav would say
to you, אנא דאמי אפילו רבנן. ana d'ami afilu Rabbanan. In general,
I could go like the Rabbis that normally say that you're פטור
when you're נתקל and then you're מפקיר. mafkir עד כאן לא פטרי
רבנן אלא במפקיר נזקיו דהכא משום דאונס הוא. ad kan lo patrei
Rabbanan ela be'mafkir nezikav de'hacha mishum de'oness hu. When did this just
clarify things we said before. When did the Rabbis say you were
פטור, meaning the Rabbis, רבי יהודה, when you're מפקיר נזקיו? mafkir nezikav?
That's by נתקל because נתקל is considered not to be negligent. So
you weren't negligent here, you weren't negligent here. אבל מפקיר נזקיו דעלמא.
aval mafkir nezikav de'alma. But let's say there was real negligence. You
know, and your thing's in the רשות הרבים reshus harabim and you're
totally negligent about it and then you renounce ownership. מחייב. mechayev. That
I would say you're חייב because that's basically the question of: do
you need to own a בור bor? or not? So what we're
now saying is, however you discuss the debate of רבי מאיר and
רבי יהודה, רב אלעזר Rav Elazar and רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan are
debating a case where you were real negligent. Your stuff you left
your hazard in רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, you left your knife sticking
out in the middle of רשות הרבים and then you were מפקיר
mafkir it, okay? So that is the basic question, not about whether
there was negligence initially. That was the basic question of are you
only חייב if you own the בור bor. or not? All right.
So even the Rabbis that normally would say that you're פטור, here
you're חייב because you created it with real negligence. All right. So
the גמרא says like this: תסתיים, tistayem, let's conclude דרב אלעזר הוא
דאמר חייב. de'Rav Elazar hu de'amar chayav. רב אלעזר Rav Elazar would
say you're חייב, which means again, remember, the real question here is:
do you have to own the בור? bor You created it with
negligence and now you are מפקיר mafkir it. Do you have to
own the בור? bor Let's say the רב אלעזר Rav Elazar is
the one who says you're חייב. דאמר רב אלעזר משום רבי ישמעאל,
d'amar Rav Elazar mishum Rabbi Yishmael, שני דברים אינם ברשותו של אדם
והכתוב עשאן כאילו הם ברשותו. shnei devarim ainam bi'reshuto shel adam ve'hakatuv
asa'an ke'ilu hem bi'reshuto. There are two things you don't really own
but the Torah treated it as if you did own to make
you responsible for it. ואלו הן, ve'eilu hen, these are they: בור
ברשות הרבים bor bi'reshut ha'rabim וחמץ משש שעות ולמעלה. ve'chametz mi'shesh sha'ot
u'lemala. A בור bor, in the public domain and חמץ chametz from
the midday of פסח Pesach onwards. You don't really own it because
it's אסור בהנאה. assur be'hana'ah. If it's אסור בהנאה assur be'hana'ah you
can't really have ownership over it, but it's enough yours that you're
liable for having חמץ chametz in your possession. Okay, and a בור
ברשות הרבים, bor bi'reshut ha'rabim, you dug it but you don't own
it because it's dug in the public domain, but it's still considered
your בור, bor. you own it for this purpose to be liable.
So what point's is, is again, now what we really just debating
is: do you have to own the בור? bor. So for since
רב אלעזר Rav Elazar says you're חייב for a בור ברשות הרבים,
bor bi'reshut ha'rabim, it's like you own it but you don't have
to really own it, okay, you are liable for having created the
hazard even if you don't own it. And רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
would say: no, you're only חייב if you actually own the בור.
bor, Okay. So the גמרא says like this: ומי אמר רב אלעזר
הכי? u'mi amar Rav Elazar hachi? Now does רב אלעזר Rav Elazar
really say that you don't have to own the בור? bor. והאמר
רב אלעזר איפכא, ve'ha'amar Rav Elazar ipcha, we see that he says
the opposite. דתנן, de't'nan, we teach in a משנה: ההופך את הגלל
ברשות הרבים. ha'hofech et ha'galal bi'reshut ha'rabim. You're turning over dung in
רשות הרבים and because, you know, animals poop in רשות הרבים and
you want to use the dung for your fertilizer, so you're hoping
to take possession of it. והוזק בהן אחר, ve'huzak bahen acher, and
as you're turning it over and moving it, some other person slipped
on it and got damaged. So it basically becomes your בור bor
now. Does your turning over of the dung make it your בור?
bor, Okay. חייב בנזקו, chayav be'nizko, you're חייב. ואמר רב אלעזר: ve'amar
Rav Elazar: לא שנו אלא שנתכוין לזכות בהן. lo shanu ela she'nitkavein
lizkot bahen. That's only if you tried to take possession of the
dung, then it's your בור. bor. אבל לא נתכוין לזכות בהן, aval
lo nitkavein lizkot bahen, but if you moved it without taking possession,
פטור, you're exempt. Now why is that? If I moved it from
place A to place B, I created a בור bor. in place
B. Even if I didn't take possession of the dung, I created
a בור. bor So if רב אלעזר Rav Elazar says I have
to take possession of it, it sounds like for רב אלעזר Rav
Elazar I'm only חייב on a בור bor. that I own, okay?
אלמא, alma, you see, מפקיר נזקיו פטור. mafkir nezikav pattur. If you
don't own it, even if you were negligent, you're exempt. So doesn't
that show you that רב אלעזר Rav Elazar says you have to
own the בור? bor. אמר רב אדא בר אהבה: amar Rav Adda
bar Ahava: no, שהחזירו למקומו. she'hechziro limkomo. Here's the story, here's why
you have to own it in that case: because you picked up
the dung and you moved it and then you said, nah, you
know what, I'm not going to bring it home, and you put
it back where you got it from. So you didn't dig a
בור. bor. So if you didn't dig the בור bor. because it's
back where it started from, you're only חייב if you took possession.
So in general he says you don't have to own it if
you dug it, but in this case you didn't dig it. You
picked up picked it up and you put it back. So in
this case you're only חייב if you own it. אמר רבינא amar
Ravina משל דרב אדא בר אהבה ל... mashal de'Rav Adda bar Ahava
le... מה דבר דומה? ma devar domeh? What would that be like
when you removed it and put it back that we're saying that
you're not liable if you don't own it? למוציא בור מגולה, l-motzi
bor meguleh, let's say you walked in רשות הרבים and you found
an uncovered pit. וכסהו v-chisahu and you decided to do a public
service and you covered it. וחזר וגילהו v-chazar v-gilahu and then you
said nah to heck with it and you removed it. So in
that case are you חייב for digging a בור bor, or do
we say, you know what, you just reversed your action, you didn't
really do anything net, you didn't do anything, and it's not your
בור, bor it's the original owner's בור. bor: So here too, I
moved the dung, I put it back, I didn't take possession, it's
not mine, I didn't do anything, and that's why you're פטור because
you didn't dig the בור. bor So אמר ליה מר זוטרא בריה
דרב מרי לרבינא מי דמי? amar lei Mar Zutra bereih de-Rav Mari
le-Ravina mi dami? No, no, no, you can't compare the cases. התם
hasam לא אסתלק ליה מעשה ראשון. lo istallek lei ma-aseh rishon. When
you covered the בור, bor when you put the manhole cover on
the pit, you didn't really erase the בור. bor There was still
a בור bor, there that was covered. So the first person's בור,
bor. it was still his בור. bor, And then you took off
your cover, it remained the first person's בור. bor, אבל הכא aval
hacha in this case when you removed the dung, אסתלק ליה מעשה
ראשון. istallek lei ma-aseh rishon. The first person's בור doesn't exist anymore.
You moved it out of the place. It's not like you put
a cover on top of it. You completely eradicated his thing. So
even when you move it back to the original place, you've now
created a new בור. Okay? לא דמי. lo dami. If you want
to make an analogy, here's the analogy: אלא למוציא בור מגולה, ela
l-motzi bor meguleh, you walk in רשות הרבים, you find a pit,
וטממו, v-timemo, you're going to do a public service and you fill
it up with dirt. And after filling it up with dirt you
say to heck with it, וחזר וחפרו, v-chazar v-chafro, you dig it
again. Now in that case you've made a בור. Okay? דאסתלק ליה
מעשה ראשון. d-istallek lei ma-aseh rishon. You erased the first person's act.
You made a בור. So here too, you moved the dung, you
erased the first person's act, even if you put it back it's
your בור. So I don't understand, according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
why is it if you don't need to own the בור, if
digging a בור is enough, why is this not enough moving the
dung and putting it back? So the גמרא says וקיימא ליה ברשותו
v-kayma lei bi-reshuso and then it becomes yours? אלא אמר רב אשי,
ela amar Rav Ashi, here's the scenario where you haven't made a
new בור: כשהפכו לפחות משלושה. kesheh-hafcho l-pachos mi-shloshah. You basically you never
really fully removed it from its place. You lifted it up less
than three טפחים. tefachim. So
we say things that are less than three טפחים tefachim are
still like they're connected to
the ground. So you didn't fully
dig up, fill up
the בור
yet. You know what I
mean? You just moved it a little bit off the ground and
then you put it back. So in that case you really didn't
do anything. And if you didn't have intention to take possession, you
don't own it and you didn't dig it. All right? And that's
why. But technically for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer you don't have to
own it. This was a case though where you had to own
it because you didn't really dig it because you lifted it up
a little bit and put it back. So now the גמרא says
ומאי דוחקיה דרבי אליעזר לאוקמה כגון שהפכו לפחות מג' u-mai duchkeih de-Rabbi
Eliezer l-ukmeh kegon she-hafcho l-pachos mi-gimel וטעמא דכי נתכוון לזכות בה אי
לא נתכוון לזכות בה לא? ve-ta-ama d-ki niskaven lizkos bah i lo
niskaven lizkos bah lo? The משנה just said that you're חייב if
you move the dung. So what made רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say,
oh, it's a case of less than three and you're only חייב
if you take possession? Why did he create that funny scenario? Just
say you don't have to take possession, as long as you move
it a significant as long as you seriously remove it from its
place. Okay? Why did he assume it was less than three and
you didn't do anything and only if you take possession? לוקמה, l-ukmeh,
let's say the משנה is talking למעלה מג'. le-ma-alah mi-gimel. You lifted
up the dung more than three. ואע"ג דלא נתכוון לזכות בה חייב.
v-af al gav d-lo niskaven lizkos bah chayav. Right? Why did he
say you have to take possession? Why did he assume according to
this way that you're explaining him, why did he assume you didn't
really move the dung and it's only if you take possession? אמר
רבא מתניתין קשיא ליה. amar Rava masnisin kashya lei. The language of
the משנה bothered him. מאי הפך לישני הגביה? mai hapach lishneih higbih?
It says if you're turning over the dung. Turning over suggests that
you haven't really moved it significantly. If you really had removed it
from its place, it would have said if you lifted up the
dung. So by saying turning over, for him that meant it was
still basically in its original place. אלא שמע מינה כל הפך למטה
משלושה הוא. ela shema mina kol hapach l-mata mi-shloshah hu. Okay, it's
under three. So therefore what have we said? We'll pick up with
this tomorrow. Unfortunately we just have a little bit left to go
but we're already a little over. So we'll wrap up with this
tomorrow. But the basic thing that we have said is, okay, רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יוחנן are debating being מפקיר נזקיו nezakav
after negligence. Okay? So and therefore the question really is, is the
בור that you're חייב on only a בור that you own? So
we assume that since רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says that there's things
you don't own that you're חייב for and one of them is
a בור, a בור ברשות הרבים. bor bi-reshus harabim. So it seems
very clear that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you do not have
to own the בור. Why does he say you have to own
the dung? That was in a case where he understood the משנה
to be you didn't really move the dung so much, so you
didn't really dig the בור, and therefore you have to own it.
But if you really did move the dung significantly... significantly and you
did dig the בור, you don't have to own it. So רבי
אלעזר says you have to own it, excuse me, you don't have
to own it, it's enough to dig it, and presumably רבי יוחנן
says you have to own it, but we're going to see tomorrow
whether we're going to stay by that way of framing their debate.
Okay, so to be continued tomorrow. Cliffhanger. Cliffhanger, yeah. Oh, I so
thought we were going to catch up. We almost did, but we
didn't finish the דף. Okay. We're good, we're good.